welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
cool okay so check-ins
yeah I just feel calm comfortable very
very grateful and happy see my good
friend Andrew so welcome to the stoah
i'm peter lindbergh the steward of the
stoah and this is a place for us to
cohere and dialogue about what matters
most at the nice edge of this moment and
we have a lighter crew today
so how it's gonna work is that it's
almost gonna be like a podcast format
where Andrew and I are just gonna riff
on the gift economy and if you have any
questions at any time just write in the
chat box and then when like a thread of
our just kind of dies down then I might
take you in to jump in so it's like a
hot potato with the podcast and you can
jump in with your question for Andrew
and then you can have a kind of exchange
and then I might jump in to get someone
else in there
or it just might be me and Andrew just
talking for for the whole 60 minutes
there's no one jumps in so that's sort
of the how today will work
I guess that being said and your do you
have any opening thoughts about today's
topic or gift economy or just there's
anything yeah yeah but if I provide here
what a gift economy is you broke up just
a little bit there I think I heard you
say
providing with a gift economy yeah it
would help if I provide I always just
look at look at around the corner you
can't help if I provide just a
two-minute overview for people who are
not a constant you yeah that's good okay
let me just provide you the thought
experiment so it's nice nice to meet
everyone it's lovely to see you today
hi let's imagine that we have three
entities a B and C and the entities
could be persons or they could
the organization's are groups so it's
just be agnostic about what these
entities are a B and C in a gift economy
what could happen is that entity a year
after a could just add a Apple hardness
give a gift to B B would receive the
gift wholeheartedly so we so far we have
one act and two wholehearted moves now
it's what's key about a gift economy at
least in my experience and they lived in
one for about a decade is that it's B
has no burden there are no debts that
are occurring to be just in virtue
haven't received a gift from me so yet
son later point could give a gift to C
now be fine and then B would give a gift
wholeheartedly to C and C we'd receive a
gift to a hard thing or at some later
point B could give a gift to a but it's
not in any way in exchange those are two
fundamentally different acts that
transpired there so you might ask
yourself what is what is actually going
on here whereas in a market system you
begin with a sense of separation between
entities that sense of separation is
perpetuated in a gift economy what's
happening if I may put it rather
poetically is that you have in and
through the set of actions we call
givings and receiving love emerging or
if I may put it a little bit less
poetically you get more and more
entanglement
so what's actually going on over the
Nylund gave you a few different acts if
you continue to iterate this process so
to speak what you begin to see is
greater and grander entanglement of
different entities with one another so
the aim of a gift economy actually is
you might say or rather poetically the
full expression of love whereas the aim
of market transactions is to maintain
separate entities as separate entities
so that's just a little starting point
and we can go from there let's take it
the whole thing about how it's a your
two ears like that that's love is an
expression of love the gift economy
I just want to agree with that and not
even look not even fully understanding
yes yes but maybe you can kind of fill
in some of the details with the gaps
there but why is that the case let me
try to give you a very concrete example
let's suppose something out of the blue
writes to me and gives me a gift of
money I have no idea who this person is
the person is giving the gift in order
to support the the philosophical life
I'm leading and I could just say thank
you that's that but that's not really
the invitation here the invitation is
for me to write back and say how are you
doing what's going on with your life or
thank you so much or here's what my life
is like so it ends up being that
particular gift ends up being initiation
into the ways in which would become more
and more entangled so there's a
wonderful quote from Martin sailings who
is a who is an anthropologist I wrote a
fundamental essay in the 1960s or so
called the original affluent society and
he says in this essay somewhere or maybe
it was in the other part of the book
called stone into economics if friends
give gifts gifts make friends it's
almost a direct quote from the book
that's a nice instantiation right you
start to realize that what's happening
in and through
multiple forms of giving and receiving
ziz that you end up getting but the
Greeks would have called philia an
incredible example of loving friendship
okay so there's a yeah I agree with that
and it resonates deeply now there's a
couple few threads to go down and I
don't have a good sense of which one to
go down
is there anything to live for you of
what to inquire into about the gift
economy like how it can manifest in
different areas how to sophistical e
sophisticatedly frame it in order to
kind of like you know engender
that love because right now I just
throwing something up on my website a
little blurb it doesn't feel
sophisticated and and your philosophical
practice when you sort of on board
someone into it you ask them specific
questions that help them kind of
understand how they can give a gift in
in sort of the right way so any kind of
line of enquiry feels alive for you I
think we should look at some concrete
cases we could look at the store we have
some people on the call who are involved
in nonprofits yeah that would be gonna
be great because I know what mine looks
like
I've been doing it now for about a
decade I'm very clear about but it would
be interesting to see what was a gift
economy actually look like in cases that
are not like the particular life I'm
leading yeah this does really good okay
so a few people just came in what we're
doing we're just sort of mean and you're
having kind of a conversation almost
like a podcast conversation but if
you're inspired to ask a question just
write in the chat box and if a thread
dies down I'll take you in and then you
could kind of ask engineer question I
think this is the right right line of
inquiry right now so maybe maybe you
could you said this before the last
session you're here at the stoah and the
kinda the inspiration of this one I just
want to seek your counsel about you know
like like personally seek your counsel
in such a way that would be beneficial
for others in order how we can kind of
use the gift economy idea the spirit of
it applied to different kind of domains
and aspects so maybe you can just do it
like a recap of how you go about your
gift economy and your philosophical
practice
and we can talk about the stoah yeah
well okay so they're you to imagine that
there are ranges between 20 and 40
people around the world with whom I
regularly philosophize and then and then
you have to imagine that we're not
involved in two different sorts of
things one is exchange so that's not the
case that the persons coming and
thinking that this is a service and the
person is somehow going to get
philosophical wisdom in exchange for
money or vice versa it's not an exchange
it's also not a donation it would take a
while to spell the difference between
what I call a gift and what I call
donation it's not a donation in the
sense that's not for example directed at
some kind of mission in this case the
gift is given to me to support my life
so I think that's enough for a starting
point now what happens is that I'm
basically interested in cultivating a
certain kind of philosophical
relationship with someone so let's call
that philosophy just to make it very
clear
so we're philosophizing in a certain way
the last time I probably described it by
thinking about a certain world that we
live in
so the philosophizing is its own thing
now because I have a body and because my
wife has a body because the body
requires food and other material needs
to be met there's another world which
we'll call the gift economy the
philosophizing which takes place at a
regular basis is its own fundamental
thing in the gift economy is something
else entirely
the reason I continue to spell it out in
this way is that the typical line of
thought is to suggest that two different
things can be compared in such a way as
to make it seem as if they're equivalent
but the fundamental understanding the
gift economy is that fundamentally
different things are fundamentally
different
so on a certain basis I can go into this
in more detail the person will offer a
gift to support and usually a form of
money to support the life that we're
leading and in aggregate all of those
gifts make up what called what I would
call live with it then I have questions
that ask people at a certain point to
make to make it very clear and plain how
we're going to understand money in this
relationship but the most basic question
is this how much are you able to give in
a wholehearted way in order to meet some
material needs
and that can always change over time
that's where it gets a little bit more
sophisticated if the person does well in
life and wishes to give more that's
wonderful
if the person is falling on hard times
and it needs to give less that's also
fine so it's a fluid dynamic motion and
the reason why it's what Nassim thali
would call an anti fragile system if you
want to get into the that language is
that there is a sufficient number of
people from different places around the
world in different industries all of
them are giving different amounts so
that if one person wishes to leave
that's fine it's still a sufficiently
anti fragile system if other people wish
to come that's fine too so one thing to
say that it speaks in favor of it is
that it differs ostensibly from what
Gnostic Tolley would call a fragile
system which is that of gainful
employment and I think I'll kind of
conclude my remarks there
so I've wanting into the weeds of the
stoah and how the Stowe is using the
gift economy how we can use it better
but first the frame I'm using I'm
viewing the stoah in this project as my
gift to the world right now do you have
that frame to with your philosophical
practice is that that you're viewing
that this is your gift you're giving to
the world yes and no which is a little
quaver quiet
yes and if we go back to the - let's
let's take this door for example so any
of these sessions for you you might call
that the philosophy world so let's say
someone comes on talks about Seneca or
Cove at 19 and since making all of that
where Adam Robert comes on and talks
about spiritual practice for women etc
etc all of these I would call philosophy
that is a gift but you'd be very careful
with people because you don't want them
to think that the gift of philosophy is
comparable to the gift that comes the
form of money or help or whatever yeah
that's why I'm tend to be very I don't
tend to use the gift to the world quite
as frequently anymore because I get a
little bit concerned that people start
to think oh if you
give to the world then I need to give
you a gift or something like that yeah
so I usually say the philosophy is about
wisdom on our understanding that's why I
use this to world dualistic analogy yeah
and that the other one's about the gift
which helps to meet the material needs
of the body so early it's a gift that
meets the material needs it's a stone if
you yeah because apartment just wants to
give this and whatever I'm doing right
here without like receiving anything I
just want to do this the stoic project
no I mean what I don't thing I learned
is that people today the degree in
spiritual circles talk about having no
expectations we've heard that a lot but
that's not really true I thought about
that before this session thing it's not
that you need to have no expectations is
that you need to begin to examine the
expectations you have and have fewer
expectations one expectation I have for
everyone within my philosophize is that
they give something because I've
actually tried in my life I've actually
tried to philosophize with people and
they don't there's no expectation they
ever give right it doesn't honestly I
mean this is not some kind of neoliberal
argument it's just it's just there needs
to be a typically need to be a little
bit skin in the game someone says thank
you that's it
you know yeah to qualify my my last
statement it wasn't necessarily tied to
the gift economy it sort of like this
whole project to me is sort of like
reading a really good book and I don't
care if anyone knows I'm reading that
book I just have that desire to do it
of course yeah so so the Stoll project
maybe I'll get some I don't know if I
mentioned it to you already
so the idea here is it's like a digital
campfire where we have kind of like a
wisdom gym forming there's a psycho like
a psycho technology incubator that
people can test out things and that
could be porting the wisdom gym and then
there's like sense-making knows where
people come in and speak like Jordan
Hall yourself or whoever and then they
have like these Q&A portions that's how
it's like forming right now and then
people have been offering or inspired to
provide gifts just based off the Lincoln
there's mentioning it the form of money
help whatnot
there has not been sophisticated
training around it like you have in your
practice which I'm hoping we can get to
but that was what's interesting that's
happening here already to digital
campfires emerge from this project
Colin Morris's who I think you you've
talked to her talking to he has a
digital dance studio but embodiment and
he's basing it off the gift economy
Tyson who's in this chat right now he's
doing a freestyle studio where is like
freestyle rap in the form of kind of
like keeping ego in check and as a form
of like you know being practicing your
truthfulness muscle in a kind of
artistic way and so he started his own
digital campfire based up the gift
economy model and so this sort of thing
is inspiring other people to do similar
things and so if we can kind of get it
right here at the stoah and it would
help other people get it right other
places as well which is I find really
cool and that Raven is in the audience
as well and she's probably gonna do her
own thing as with that with the gift
economy as well so that being said is
there any before I kind of like ask you
about how to make it more sophisticated
the framing everything any kind of
thoughts on how the stoic could are
currently is operating on the gift
economy yeah I was thing about this
before our session today and I found
that I think it may have said this I
mean the last gift economy session that
you have to be really clear about the
question you ask people or the earthy
prefer the invitation you make right now
the invitation I think is it's too vague
so the the vagueness of the institution
will be manifested and often in the
vagueness of the responses are
non-responsive
if I ask if I if I just ask a question
can you give something just people
people some would say yes and would say
no it wouldn't be clear what they would
give and so forth so I like the thing
about when I'm philosophizing people so
one of the criteria is to provide an
answer that's very plain and clear and
just answer that question so if I ask
someone how old he or she is that person
would just need to give the H that's it
that's the answer to that question yeah
if I ask the
and what sorts of things do you remember
from yesterday that's a little bit of a
vague or questions going to present some
a little bag here of an answer if I
asked the person what's the meaning of
life I would expect that answer to be
broader and more abstract less concise
and so on what I'm trying to illustrate
is that right now the what I would I
noticed is that a lot of the nonprofit's
seem to have very unclear articulations
of what they're asking from people I'll
give you an example I went to the
garrison Institute which is in upstate
New York in the fall where I was at a
retreat with a spiritual teacher named
Rupert spire who's in the invite but
thought to direct path for those who are
interested and as you might imagine the
garrisons to another such places that
have largely been these in-person
retreats have been struggling mightily
during covin 19 so they've they've
pivoted to a virtual sanctuary and
they've they recently just this morning
or asking for donations and again I
argue that donations are slightly
different from gifts but it was it was
you know someone who is very think has
been in this space for a while but it
still felt as if something was missing
for example I've only been there once is
it really going to be the case then
likely to be someone who's going to
contribute a donation to support this
organization the answer is probably not
so something is gone so and something is
going awry there when you just have a
vague invitation sent out to your
listserv with the view to getting some
some people to offer donations it feels
as though there was an opportunity was
missed that that it lacked the
fine-grained rail the fine-grained
nature of asking a good question of
someone who might be interested in
giving a gift yeah so with what's coming
up is a desire to state kind of like
what I want yes yes so and then we can
maybe tease out some questions so it's
basically I want what you want or what
you have a bit in a different context so
I want to continue
doing what feels like a felt sense level
is is doing something that I want to do
for its own sake
by doing the store or whatever whatever
is happening right here and I like the
idea if I could be doing this while
having my livelihood supported just like
you you know you you support yourself
you support you beautiful wife Alexandra
you have a house that's beautiful and
then you're doing what I what seems to
me is your greatest gift to the world
that you're giving that and so I want
just to support my livelihood I don't
need to be greedy would be good to have
some little bit money in the bank for a
rainy day type of thing like that I want
to live in a small town with Camille or
a monastery when I move to the monastic
Academy we got invited to stay there so
something like that would be quite
beautiful and as you know you've been
kind of advising me on like the framing
of the gift economy who's that little
blurb like and then my schpeel at the
end where I say if you want to give it a
gift in return like no no cut that
out like yeah it makes the hundred
percent and then there's a part of me
when I kind of this is why I'm just like
waiting to think about this with to talk
to you because I haven't really been
thinking about this much to be honest I
know cuz there's so much other
going on but there's like a dirtiness -
it feels like kind of being more clear
on this it's almost like I feel like one
of those those those cam girls who have
like a Amazon wishlist like I mean like
you know a skateboard or something like
that like hey if I being too clear with
it but I like the idea this this came to
mind when you're talking just maybe
having it on the gift economy webpage at
the stoah having clear like baby
basically stating what kind of life I
want or what kind of like you know
livelihood I need or whoever and then
having questions that could help people
inform them on what gifts to give yes
yeah it's it's not it's not dirty people
want to know I'll give you an example
that might illustrate the difficulty of
being in this space if you ever go to a
Buddhist retreat or some other place
sometimes there's talk about Donna which
was the Buddhist term for generosity or
gift and at some places such as the
Goenka of a Boston retreat
there is no
it's a very clumsy how they have it set
it up and given that I've been in
thinking about this for a while but
they'll basically say there are a few
things that are mistaken but the one is
just give give out of Donna based on how
much you've benefited so no no that's
that's that's that's egoistic and so
that that's not the right creating but
even if you didn't grant that you still
don't know at the end of ten day retreat
you have nothing to you don't know what
the organization needs you don't you've
no idea of no way to kind of set some
kind of coordinates or guidelines even
if you even if you wanted to give which
is pretty reasonable after ten days of
receiving throughout the quarter
eautiful retreat you're just not you're
not all clear and the unclarity reveals
itself from the fact that you don't
really know what appropriate responses
so I've basically been in that situation
number of times and other people I've
spoken with have been in that situation
number of times it's very refreshing
there for it to have some clarity oh you
need shoes okay well I think I can
provide shoes here are some shoes oh you
need firewood you're living in rural
Appalachia okay well I would love to
provide you the firewood I can see how
that would function or we fill out your
life so I think we need to turn it
around and say that it's it's not being
kind of gross or weird to be specific
with people if someone wants to be if
Philip wants to be generous then someone
wants to know there's a form in which
that generosity can manifest itself and
then it's going to be a wholeheartedly
received if I just give something
vaguely to you or if I get something out
of some abstract sense I don't know
whether you're going to really it's
going to land yeah I like that that's
the expectation of giving you know we
know what this is like to give you a
simple example when we have birthdays
and your parents give you a kiss you
realize the extent to which they don't
understand to you right there's a
certain sense which I you didn't see
what it was that I really needed yeah
yeah I think you and I will have a
history
ya know that's when I'm kind of called
that out to kind of that feeling of
dirtiness I had and then just
articulating a potential Avenue our way
to move forward it just disappeared too
so I think as the next steps just sort
of like having maybe what do you think
about this so and maybe you can review
the draft like I crate like like a blurb
of like what as of this moment what kind
of life I would like or what kind of you
know how I would like my livelihood to
be supported and what letter I kind of
require for that and then just kind of
ask some questions like wisely design
questions in order to inform people how
to provide a gift and then the actual
means of how to provide it either PayPal
or whatever or help or support yeah and
then I would say that's good that kind
of to replace that one is it's always
it's almost always wise not to put too
many questions on there the question is
really meant to be it's a very Michi and
it kind of it channels the dionyza
energy into a form to an Apollonian form
right so if you have 20 questions it
shows a kind of anxiety you know I don't
want that just a few nice questions
helps to true direct people's attention
to what really matters yes yes as well
so coming up to mind is um there's um
part of those thought oh there's a
nonprofit that kind of organizes all the
stoical groups in the world and there
was tension there between me and um when
I launched a stole a project they
thought like was this kind of directed
with the profit motive is he like she's
trying to be a hustler and stuff and so
there was like a disconnect there but I
chatted with one of the board members
was I'm on the board I'm on the board as
well
we charged in the comment level setted
and it's interesting I think it's
important to be clear about all that
upfront with kind of like humility
because it will disabuse people of
having these ideas that you're doing
something that you're actually not doing
yes cool so yeah I'll send you that when
I have that ready and I mean we can kind
of pivot to the group now we have 30
minutes left
since we only have 12 people there's two
things ways we can do it we can just
have my open popcorn style anyone can
just unmute themselves little trust your
discernment or we can do the Q&A in the
chat box which is your sense Andrew for
for this lets a lot of people to use the
discernment yeah okay so I'm gonna go in
grid view and then anyone who feels I
think everyone has the ability to unmute
themselves yes you do
so if you feel called to just unmute
yourself just to ask anything to Andrew
or even me or just to the group feel
free to do so yeah good question so
Peter is this your sort of main source
of income or is it is a side project for
you like what's your situation with
running this because I'm just wondering
why you're saying supporting your
lifestyle and your income from what
degree is you rely on this to sort of
help you alone yeah so I'm a trainer at
Dale Carnegie Training it's like a
interpersonal kind of training company
has been around for hundred years and
they're probably gonna go out of
business because all their bread and
butter is in person training so I'm not
doing any training right now and my wife
works full-time remotely so we're not
one night we have a bunch of cash and
savings so I'm not worried about that
and so there's an option there's a fork
in the road do I find like some Normie
job you know like that I couldn't work
from remote where am I gonna go full
throttle with this thing and I decided
to go full throttle with this thing
maybe about a month ago alright I didn't
have a choice really I'm just following
the Damon I'm just going for it
and and people have been gifting me
money not enough to support a livelihood
but it's substantial and it's allowing
me to buy things to support the project
and whatnot so I think I'm gonna make a
run for this and I want to do what
Andrew does with his philosophical
practice I want to support my live of it
and ideally Camille's live of it my wife
on the gift economy okay yeah because
I've read some of your blog posts
I've read a little bit about this store
background this is only my third session
so I don't really know where you're
coming from financially and also I guess
the philosophical ethos at your turn and
run the whole project with so far
because both first things I think and
what you've just said really you're
gonna change how you have to word I mean
I personally wouldn't you use its own
gift economy but I understand why it is
used the way that you approach people
for money
I mean I'd most self and I well I'm now
a student but I have been producing
music for about five or six years and
DJing and I've made like zero dollars
from it because I just you there as a
project of passion but I'm not having to
support a wife and I'm not having to I'm
not in your situation so it is a bit
different the questions I think Andrew
was saying about asking people that and
saying like if you have something like
do you feel you enjoy what we're doing
here at this door project maybe consider
giving a gift that lets like stage one
of asking for maybe arms then stage two
you start asking the more specific
questions like would you like to
continue learning with us it would
really help us out and help my life out
if you could consider donating be more
concrete about using the word donate
rather than gift or something will vague
that make sense I want to I would say
something I want to bounce it to Andrea
I'm curious I think he has more wisdom
here than I do like one thing that
there's I'm in a lucky grateful position
I'm not like stressed to get money your
support live with my wife
pretty good money and again I could I
could jump back into the old game a
world right now if I wanted to with a
little bit of a hustle I don't want to
and I also can seek out probably
investors for this project at this point
I know a lot of rich people who were
digging this project I'm friends looking
Angie Strickler from co-founder of
Kickstarter and I probably couldn't seek
his wisdom how to get offense to
investors for this and he's probably
gonna be in the wisdom gym as well but I
want to go down that path yet and I can
bring a lot of attention this project I
go on a podcast circuit got all
this North egoic noise coming this way I
don't want that yet either
I really resonate with what Andrews
doing and it feels pure and so I want to
run with that at least for the time
being
so I think that I'll pass it over to
Andrew see if he has anything out here
okay
so it'd take a little while to parse a
lot of these terms but let's come back
to the first phrasing if you enjoy
what's going on here consider giving or
donating so that that's not quite that
would be in the spirit of a donation you
might say but not in the spirit of a
gift the reason is that it doesn't I try
to give you an example last time let's
take the example of a church let's
suppose that you're a member of a church
if you're member of a church it doesn't
really matter so to speak whether you
enjoy or not enjoy the church on any
given occasion you're committed to being
a member of that church it doesn t
matter in a great sense whether the
sermon was very good on that day it'd be
nice if it were good but it might not
have been that good you're giving you're
giving I'm going to use the word gift
here you're giving a gift a certain
amount might be a tight in order that
the church will continue on for the sake
of the other congregants and for the
sake of future congregants that's the
key to that particular understanding of
giving a gift there yeah so usually a
donation might arise out of having
received something and then it's
often pointed at let's say a cause let's
say you want to stop malaria and certain
area of Africa but the gift the reason I
use the term is that it's a little bit
there's a bit more play in it comes out
of the the feeling of gratitude which is
then transferred into an act for the
sake of the other be it Peter or the
stoah be a person or the church yeah
quit so would you not say that the Snowy
is a cause though in that you could say
it is a cause to further human knowledge
and further a sense of community of
intellectuals and people who'd like to
think and connect or is when you say
cause he's saying something that's much
more definitional let's let's come back
just just just for a moment remember
what it's like to it's very hard to this
point from modernity because most of
civil society has been eviscerated so
it's it's really hard to recall what
it's like to be a part of some kind of
group to which you belong and from which
you receive let's imagine that you
belong to a choir group see where my
background is let's suppose the choir
group somehow needs to be supported an
ongoing way it's not it's not really the
case that there's a cause it's just the
case that there is something that you
all love to do for its own sake to its
singing or the beauty of singing
together you know I'm trying to give a
sense of what it's actually like to
support something which is what alasdair
macintyre would call kind of an inner
Tilos there's it exists for its own sake
for the sake of those who come to it but
not for the sake of something else if
anything comes from the stoah then it
comes as a kind of epiphenomena or a
byproduct or something else in fire
my hunch and I'm not been to Evaristo
event and obviously Peter has is that
people are coming to this over and over
again if they are for the sake of
something they can't put their words on
but for the sake of something that is
definitely here they feels it there the
right place it's a bit like finding your
your tribe or finding your scene that
then the gift comes to support having
found that scene and so that other
people can also enjoy it appreciated
yeah I mean I just want to add to that
yeah I feel really uncomfortable to
instrumentalize this whole project the
one cause or some kind of propositional
statement of a cause because I'm trying
to figure out what this is about myself
and and I'm drawn to it and I think
other people are drawn to it as well I
I'd love to oh sorry I just
I'd love to just chime in on just
something because I love this
conversation and I'm hearing the various
distinctions and how to see this and
different lenses and I don't think there
is a right answer right now when there's
a discovery process here and you know
one of the things that you brought up
around church is that while I might be
tithing to the church I do get to choose
which church I tied to so if the sermon
over three-week period just starts like
not touching my soul I may decide okay
I'm gonna continue to tithe but not the
church I'm gonna tie the different
church specifically so there is some
aspect of that donation being being
there it's being a donation that's
directed towards a specific cause the
cause that I'm directing it towards is
bringing people together on Sunday and
rippling out the most love to the world
you know into that community I think in
terms of gift I often find that like is
a cause a human being or is a human
being it's like wow this person I'm
inspired by the way you be and the way
that you live and I'd like to gift you
this because I want to see you continue
to succeed
all the ways that you do it's not a
cause towards the animal rights thing
that you're doing or it's not a it's not
your music you're kind of doing a little
bit of everything your philosophizing
your Facebook liveing you're an
influencer you're doing all sorts of
stuff I want to gift you in that way so
those are some of the lenses that I'm
seeing it through again
no no convincing one way or another
right yet I swear jump in I was meant to
be enticing her privately mentioning
each other and then I googled you and it
looks like you you you you're involved
in something called a gift economy if
I'm not mistaken could you speak a
little bit about that okay and I wanted
to first listen more here before I
started giving you an you know new great
inputs of information but but since
you're asking so I do have gift economy
calm a platform that I'm intending on
using that as a educational hub and
various you know a platform that brings
this conversation together so articles
videos that might come from the zoom
chat might come on to that platform or
to that website and then gift karma is
the name that I've come up with for an
app that essentially takes the concept
that we're talking about and and then
gamify is this process uses you know
creates a reputation score on the
platform not just for the net gifts that
you give but like how many gifts did you
give how many did you receive you know
publicizing that reputation or
privatizing it kind of like a social
scoring score or social scoring system
like China does except instead of the
government doing it to us we're creating
that social scoring system with the
gamified actions that we're taking in
terms of giving and receiving on the
platform so that's kind of the high
level in a nutshell and the idea is gift
economy becomes this platform that has a
series of apps and content that
essentially ushers in a new culture of
giving on this planet not as a
replacement to the current
see but more as a supplement an
alternative and eventually you know it
could be that it it becomes the leading
leading force over time but not
necessarily saying money is bad money is
evil let's build this it's acknowledging
the layer of the seven-layer cake that
money does you know occupy and still
recognizing that there's more layers to
our to the way that we resource you know
and and collaborate and cooperate and
how do you find yourself in this
discussion like how do you find your way
here Tyson mr. Tyson flows is a friend
and we have a ton of mutual friends as
well in daniel eisenman and mystic
misfits and different people so so I got
into this conversation he knows I given
a talk about the gift economy a few
years ago at a conference or rather like
a retreat that we were at and so he
knows that I'm I've been pushing this
concept a lot and I'll finish in just
the next thirty seconds which is I've
gone back and forth in terms of like
what are my motivations to doing gift
economy and why am i doing gating and
there is an aspect of it where I'm just
like I'm sick and tired of the money
system and I want to build this
system that changes the game and what
I'm finding though whenever I have that
mindset it's like wait hold on like let
me first get my solidified systems at
least at some level on the in the muggle
world and the current paradigm economics
and let me really show up to the gift
economy conversation and this effort
from an empowered space and not from a
place of neediness and so not trying to
fill that void with this platform but
more so see my efforts in the gift
economy as a gift like I'm here as a
gift or as somebody that's giving
forward to society into the you know
creating of a new
whole new beautiful world as Charles
Eisenstein Stein would say you know so
that's yeah that's that's why I'm not
cool well that's some glad you're here
appreciate that yeah thank you thank you
for having this conversation
Andrew was anything alive for you I
throw out something for Andrew and I'm
just wondering how you think of the so
called trading economy which I also hear
about where people want to just trade
specific trade transactions versus the
gift economy and as distant as an
example I'm a coach later in life having
been an attorney earlier in life and
they're you know there's a lot of that
that goes on in those worlds where
there's a I'll trade you this service
for that service and maybe people are
even looking at I'll trade you coaching
for vegetables or you know other
materials like that that's more of a
specific transaction so I don't I'm
guessing you don't think of that as so
much a gift as you use it and then
there's also the issue and something
like coaching as you know where there's
a downside to being pro bono because
there's no skin in the game so that adds
another dimension so do you look at the
idea of trade specific trading is just
totally different than the gift economy
or maybe a subset yeah I have so it's
it's it's it's kind of a transition case
so I typically frame things in the
following way if you ask yourself how
human beings are Homo sapiens Homo
sapiens sapiens ended up surviving I
only think seeing three basic models one
we've lived off the land in various ways
so you think of hunters and gatherers
and then you can also think of the
invention of Agriculture around ten to
twelve thousand years ago and you can
think of American poet Wendell Berry as
someone who's argued that we need to
return to land and live off with it in a
humble kindly manner that's one the
second one is the invention and
utilization of markets specifically the
form of transactions trades or exchanges
the third one is the hard one to
describe its
it's it's it's no I call it the gift so
typically what happens with people is
that they as it began to question let's
say the ubiquity of the market system
they begin to cast about and they look
for some alternatives and the first
alternative seems to be barter or trade
it's not bad it's not bad this sense
that a coaching yeah I have one person I
speak with who trade trades coaching
sessions for yoga sessions that's fine
but it's a good transition case it does
suggest that there's something that I
can offer and something that you can
offer and we won't we won't mediate it
through the use of money that's fine but
I don't think it quite goes far enough
because really what you care about is
being with that person let's just make
it clear right you if you're offering a
coaching session and that person is
offering intern yoga session really what
you're doing okay I'll give you an
example from a friend of mine he's in
his 60s he says that what meant ended by
the way he's an older man so this is
kind of what men tend to do sort of
statement says what men tend to do is
that they need the relationships through
some kind of thing they can't just talk
to one another they have to watch
football and kind of look over and chat
or they have to play some kind of sport
and while they're while they're tossing
a football back and forth they talk
about something seriously I think what's
happening here with this this notion of
trade or barter with with regard to
certain relationships is that there's
not yet the foregrounding of the
relationship what gift we're giving in
the sense I use it tends to do is it
finally foregrounds the relationship
that you care about you finally realize
that that's what's substantively at
stake here and so the gift is the gift
is sort of the secondary part that helps
to mediate the and so to speak lubricate
the relationship and I think we notice a
difference if someone comes over and and
out of the blue gives you a gift
it feels so heartwarming
expect anything from let's just remember
that experience and gives you a gift out
of the blue and so heartwarming it's so
lovely can I speak to that it's two
points there I'll put my first one my
second point first what you were saying
about a heartwarming gift so I just
recently did that for my best friend
he's sort of been in dire straits
recently had suicidal ideation and had a
suicide attempt and this had quite bad
depression and I had told him you
probably all know the show mr. Rogers
neighborhood or have heard of it in the
past and I told him about mr. Rogers and
sort of just the simple kindness that he
showed and I had phone call with him and
I sung him the song it's you I like
because I know who I knew who was in
that sort of mindset where he needed
someone to show him or even gift him
care and at the end of I think it was
the morning after I said hey give me
your dress mate went onto Amazon and I
ordered him a book of Mister Rogers
quotes and I said this is my gift to you
put this on the side of your bed and
anytime you feel sad or you don't feel
cared for just flip your page and think
of me and that my gift here is just my
unconditional care and love and that is
just what I wanted to speak on on what
you you'll print out your last point was
that when we given a gift like that out
of the blue and without any need for
reciprocation or wanting the return it
positively enlightens our soul that's
very beautiful
thank you there is very heartwarming I
mean that that nails it it's that I hope
that everyone heard that because that's
really the spirit of a gift that's
exactly right
and um and then there's non-attachment
so you can't keep telling the story ten
years from now and you had to let go of
it so there's an attachment but it's a
second point as well so we in the form
of a gift run was saying he was doing
like a quid pro pro of coaching for
another service and now service for
service is sort of a little bit
different I don't have a job currently
so I do try to give money when I can and
but with me I have quite a lot of skills
in my repertoire and what I'd like to do
if is when I see it as a project or a
person or idea that I fully support and
I want to see flourish is that I'll
approach that person and offer my skills
or offer to collaborate with them in the
form of what I turn is a gift to help
the project move on or improve or like
I've been writing for about six years so
I'll say hey if you just need to like
promote posts or if you need me to help
proofread or edit or something do it for
free because I believe in this project
and I want to see is see it move forward
would you say that is part of the gift
economy or is that still sort of like a
unmarketable type thing Oh since I think
it's the case is probably not thick
enough I mean to discern but let's
suppose that you saw something that you
really cared about that seems to be the
case let's suppose also that you are
clear about the extent of your
commitment otherwise it'll turn into a
volunteer position of some kind so your
fruit you clear that it's rather scoped
so to say and you're clearly eerily
looking for nothing in return you know
so it's not so to speak like some kind
of Weasley internship or something like
that then then it looks like a gift
now usually what happens here is that
people will have altered the really
interesting part of the point of
spiritual practice is that you have to
very much investigate your intentions
because if it comes to pass the way
you're really doing is you're you you
say it's a gift but in truth you're at
the Art Gallery this is before copan
dean so that you could be an intern so
that you become fully hired and so forth
then it's fine it's certainly a
networking strategy but that's no longer
a gift that's just a right it's a it's a
way to get yourself gainfully employed
yeah I also think not so much with gifts
but with Western altruism there's a
sense that there's a lot of people who
practice altruism now but not for the
sole cause of altruism of compassion and
empathy what they're doing is they're
practicing altruism say giving money to
a homeless person because they want that
responsive I've done something good I've
done my part and they just they want a
dopamine response but they're not doing
it just out of kindness and compassion
they're wanting something out of it
and it is really something that happens
in Western cultures in Eastern cultures
like in Thailand there's a Buddhist arms
which is it's not a reciprocation it's a
communal type thing and I don't really
know too much about so-called gift
economies you know Eastern cultures
other than that but that there's an
example for contrast great so the
important point here no no we have about
five minutes left so I'm going to open
it up for anyone else so I'll make this
brief is that one reason I like this
alternative economy which we've been
calling a gift economy is that it
actually does require a purification of
your intentions so
you need to know that you're giving a
gift of guilt not egotism but really out
of loving kindness when Buddhism that
would be called meta I give this for the
sake of the other and and and in
Aristotle is makes similar he talks
about true friendship in terms of what I
called philia that is I care for this
person for his or her own sake so that's
that's the kind of the essence of the
practices to learn that but in the way
that we have just about four minutes
left so is there anyone else who would
like to offer something so I just just
jump in and you you have to go right at
the hour could you say maybe make five
ten minutes after just to feel again
yeah so anyone who hasn't spoken yet and
you've got something feel free to shop
off mute yes you have your hand up Jean
thank you I'm just wondering if you can
think back in you know prehistory as a
word for both Peter and Andrew was the
gift response perhaps the the origins
the genesis of of all our economies you
know can you imagine perhaps a tribal
setting of prehistoric humans just
simply one person giving a gift to
another and that led gradually to the
the trading of the market economies and
everything that we have now then a
second thing that just thought we could
riff on a little bit is if it's
something in a negative context it would
be considered by most of society to be a
negative for example somebody wanted to
give a gift to the NRA or to the white
supremacy movement or something like
that how should we treat that in the
overall society do we all have free will
to gift whatever we want
or is it um should there be some I don't
know moral constraints about about all
of that
gelareh sure I'll take a crack at those
hard questions let's see what you think
no no okay all right so the first one
I'm not enough of a historian of
anthropology to build a quite answer but
I can I can I can venture a hunch and
let's just call it a hunch the hunted be
that within a tribe you can have in some
tribes the circulation of gifts so if
you want to I can point me some
literature on that so this is within the
tribe circulation of gifts on the
assumption that at a certain level of
development in a hunter-gatherer tribe
you're going to have the dispersal of
gifts according to the needs of this
particular ensemble that's probably true
I think you usually begin to notice and
anthropologists and historians of
economics will correct me if I'm wrong
that the the trading occurs between
tribes so this is what's really
interesting I think we still have that
that intuitions is what I've written
about in the recent years the intuition
is that to to your friends and the
substantive sense you give gifts to
those who are strangers you transact we
still have that intuition this is why it
seems strange to us this is why PayPal
is a completely anomalous right neela
jism because you don't pay your pals you
would never pay your pals you give gifts
to your pals it's also why the sharing
economy is anomalous too it's not a
sharing economy that's just game a in a
different form Aaron B was being he was
never a sharing economy it was always
just a hospitality industry we really
feel that in our sense that if you're
really going to share something with
someone that looks as though it's a
relationship or friendliness or
friendship if you're going to exchange
with someone that looks as though it's
someone with whom you don't want to have
a friendship it's a stranger when you
trust in a very minimal sense that's
that's my first take the second one I'm
not really sure how to answer the
question about whether or not we should
limit gifts given to say to NRA and I've
never really thought about that very
much I guess the question would be if
you granting the granting the existence
of this entity would it be the case that
gifts would be such as to make it so
powerful as to be hegemonic or dominant
in that society that's the best I can do
at this point that is to say if you were
to allow for gifts to be given to the
point at which the NRA becomes so huge
became so huge that gun ownership became
so great that the effects of gun
ownership were so bad for Americans
which it probably is it's the best I can
say I'm not really sure but thank you
for your questions I love just this to
speak into this you know if I have a
customer that comes to my store and I I
know that he has a history of stealing
you know do I say sorry no shirt no
shoes no stealers you know no service
you know like do I is it on me to stop
that transaction or that interaction
with him because I'm not because I judge
his actions to be out of alignment with
my moral value code and I've wrestled
with that and the truth is is that we're
connected to every person anyways and
it's not my decision or my choice to say
if I'm gonna do that if I want to I will
but not from a should place but from a
desire do I want to interact with this
person or not and I think that having
the hood or the rules around it for
ourself or for others I think we can
just speak to it that like hey when
we're gifting we are putting energy into
something we are watering that plant and
if that plant is a weed then that weeds
gonna get bigger and so it's just part
of the knowledge that we go into it with
that awareness so that's that's like one
point I wash air and then as far as the
second point with with Andre talking
about like it's a it's a bridge right
way I'm not sure sorry I don't remember
who started this but in terms of giving
like if you're giving because you want
to get the recognition that you're this
generous person well that's okay that
could be a bridge because you might do
it for the external validation in the
ego and your wife is
you know think you're hot stuff because
you gave you know you're giving and
you're such an amazing macho guy that's
helping the world and then after that
you get the return on investment of the
ripple of impact report from that gift
and you find out that oh my god all
these kids were fed all these people and
your heart opens up so potentially you
might have done it for the egoic you
might have done it cuz you wanted to get
laid you might have done it for all the
reasons I I can tell you because I've
done it for all the reasons myself so
I'm not talking about them I'm talking
about myself and but then after a while
by putting myself in that situation and
there's a little kid there that's
smiling and you know and I'm tearing up
because I'm remembering when I was a kid
my heart opens up and this essentially
supported me getting there which is why
I've been thinking that this gift
economy movement is a combination of
education conversation like we're doing
here and also tools and platforms that
help train somebody kind of like the
health app or Fitbit or something where
people run more with Fitbit not because
the Fitbit actually makes you run more
but because you like seeing that score
go up you're doing it for the scoring
reason you're doing for the seemingly
wrong reasons but then you're like
I look good you know I'm just gonna keep
running because I feel good in my body
and so the Fitbit was serving as a
effective bridge I have a question the
surface and my curiosity is around like
if I have a gift that I am interested in
giving because I love to give it so
gathering people around a freestyle
campfire giving a gift of an experience
and yeah I want to be in right
relationship with the parts of me that
want to mark it and promote and brand
because I think then there will be a you
know because I want to receive gifts as
well and I think that and I want a lot
of people to come with these experiences
but I notice myself yeah like wanting to
proceed with caution in a way
I don't want to bring I want to be wise
about what game a things I've taken on I
bring into this relationship and what I
completely leave behind so I'm just
curious about any thoughts about how to
be in right relationship with that right
I just want to double click and support
that comment because that's a challenge
that I find with the whole stole a
project of like like I could market it
more aggressively but I'm not because I
like the slow build of attracting the
right people I don't think we have the
sort of the ability to transmute noise
into signal right now or kind of keep
you going check if too much ego comes in
too fast so I'm really curious what and
remember you had a few not sure what the
question is exactly if I were to
rephrase it it's like Tyson he has this
free style through a pandemic every
Saturday it was a really quality
session and he has his own digital
campfire that he has a few sessions that
he's stewarding and then the idea is how
to wisely market to bring more people
and to find out about it without sort of
you know I guess attracting the wrong
people or marketing in the wrong way
where you're maybe marketing it out of
ego or gamy purposes why do you need to
why do you need to market it ok well
then this might be a way to add into the
question is being in right relationship
with the like reliance on a receiving
gifts and yeah so maybe like if there
was ever a time for you Andrew where you
found yourself in feeling a sense of
need for a gift for it like your
security or well-being or health may be
that situation has happened maybe not
how did you approach like maybe making
your offering more widely available or
more findable found more more awareness
so that you might then attract more
people to philosophize with so then that
you might receive
more gifts and take better care of your
needs and so for me I guess I just have
I I noticed these like hesitations or
this caution about marketing and like
spreading something and because of the
part of me that is like wants the gifts
that are going to come from doing that
you just have to investigate I mean I
hate to to make it sound very spiritual
do you have to investigate what you just
said there I mean I've never really
marketed I've just you know if I may
speak and like a Sufi I'd say I do the
best that philosophizing and let God
take care of the rest
you can put that in stoical terms if you
want to you know see what's within my
powers and I will let the rest of it
lest of its a more fatty that's you know
you know it's it seemed like a ton
traumatic answer but you have to kind of
investigate that feeling of meat and
feeling a want contraction because if
you know you know the trust comes in the
following manner if if this is a
beautiful thing it's a truly beautiful
thing then people will find it
that's just
Bishan sits as well let's do Tom last
question and then we'll close up Thanks
yeah so be sort of pragmatic I think
what Tyson and Peter are getting at is
different than what you're doing Andrew
and maybe what Ron is doing because I
think Ron and Andrew biased I believe
are working one-on-one with individuals
and then sort of negotiating or going
through a series of questions of what
can you give me or give me where as
Peters got you know a bunch of us
collected here Tyson it sounds like you
also are collecting people you know like
a group so my question is and to throw
in an opinion quickly to Roger I'm a
little worried that there's too much
reliance on Gideon's people's ego into
having a score about what they're giving
which is kind of the market economy of
especially nonprofits in which people
who love just everybody's know how great
they are anyways there's there's a the
question for me is maybe this can help
Peter and Tyson Andrew how would you
help them besides what I assume is
they'd have to ask me individually how
would you help them increase those of us
who may want to give something to them
but we need to be asked okay so I like I
think you got this time I like fine fine
grains well-tuned
responses so the first thing we said
occurred earlier which is that on the
website I would make the what you might
call the ask much clearer much much
clearer what is it what is what does
Peter say really need and so he has to
know himself much better than was
presented so far another thing you could
do if you wanted to the other thing that
I always do and this is not because it's
not location is that whatever someone
gives a gift I will write right back to
that person that's the person wants to
know that I received the gift and
received it well and I want to know
something about the person
so that's a way of developing a
relationship with that person and that's
something that Peter and enticing could
you but then the third thing that could
be really interesting is that some
people want to as people say they'd be
vulnerable then they could actually say
look Peter do you wanna have a
conversation I can offer we can talk
about what would be a reasonable gift
for you to offer for me to offer you you
could do some of those sessions that
would give him a sense of what people
are how their people are thinking this
is not market research it's just way of
understanding what people are actually
thinking and it's a way for him to
actually learn to learn to be much more
comfortable around money I've been doing
something like that for 10 years and
there it's actually a spiritual practice
of learning what it's like to listen
very openly very non-judgmentally to
what someone is saying to the point at
which that person feels as if he or she
can give whole hardly whatever it is and
not in reference to what someone else
would give or might give or not a
reference to what that person would like
to give in other words I don't missus
lease if one wants to be very intimate
about this I don't see a way around the
needs to actually have some
correspondences the people gift
economies are very messy in my
experience of gifticon is it's very
touchy it's it's very tactile there's a
lot of touching that goes on
it's Winnicott would say there's a lot
of holding a lot of holding and touching
so that's that's the kind of issue the
pithy responses that find a way to have
lots of holds and touches very cool so
for my commitment I will continue
learning out loud with this project in
front of you all and and brother Andrew
will be along for the ride I imagine
that being said Andrew thanks so much
for coming today and sharing your
thoughts and engaging with us any
closing thoughts on your end no just
thank you very much for having me or
they enjoy the conversation I enjoyed
meeting a lot of you today it's good
wonderful to see you again sometime
mhm and I thank everyone for coming out
today I'm really gunshot about the gift
economy right now so yeah I'll let
myself
collect my thoughts and just share this
link and the time being in the chat box
and I'll mention briefly for the
upcoming events for today yeah we just
have one this afternoon at 6:00 p.m.
Eastern Time like Shane breakthrough
boot camp with AJ bond he was ashamed
you cater here in Toronto it's wonderful
sessions about how to like build a
relationship with Shane individually and
collectively so check that out on the
website all right one thanks so much
you ok here I go and you closes it all